CURRICULUM VITAE Gianluca Alfieri

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Nationality: Italian

Date of birth: 28th July 1978

• Andress: Piazza Dalla Chiesa 41 D, Fiumicino (RM), Italy

Email: alfieri.g@adr.it

Telephone: +39 335 1550792

CAREER PROFILE

I'm an experienced and versatile manager with a consolidated know-how of the air transport sector, particularly in management of airport operations and connected risk. This has been developed in a company that manages the main Italian airport system consisting of both Fiumicino and Ciampino Airports (totalling 42 million passengers/year), with approximately 2500 employees and a turnover of more than 600 M€/year. Reporting to the COO (and to the CEO between 2010 and 2011) I'm responsible for the safety management system of both the airports, certified by the Italian Civil Aviation Authority (ENAC). Furthermore I have strong leadership and team working skills demonstrated in coordinating internal departments, airport authorities and operators for all activities related to safety, in the operational, maintenance, infrastructure design and management of emergency areas. Moreover I have gained significant experience of managing complexity and project management.

WORK EXPERIENCE

FROM SEPTEMBER 2010 TO PRESENT - AEROPORTI DI ROMA S.P.A.

- Head of Safety Management and Fiumicino and Ciampino Airports Safety Manager
 - Main activities and responsibilities:
 - Management and development of the Safety Management System of Fiumicino and Ciampino Airports
 - Employee management and budgeting of the Safety Management Department and related offices: Airport Certification, Reporting and Risk Management, Ciampino Safety Management Activities
 - Coordination of the activities related to the CAA airport certification
 - Coordination of airport authorities and operators for the activities related to safety
 - Coordination of internal departments engaged in safety issues, related to air-side operations, maintenance, infrastructures design and management of emergency response plan for aircraft accidents
 - Operational and infrastructural risk management
 - Management of internal/external audits for processes related to safety (compliance monitoring)
 - Management of the airport reporting system of aeronautical incidents
 - Management of airport manuals containing operational, maintenance and design procedures
 - Compliance of the airside infrastructure initiatives with the national and international safety standards (CAA, EASA and ICAO) and management of related risk assessment or aeronautical studies
 - Managing the relations with the Flight Safety National Agency (ANSV)
 - Training of airport staff on safety management systems
 - **○** CAA airport certifications achieved:
 - Three-year renewal of Fiumicino airport certificate in 2012
 - Three-year renewal of Ciampino airport certificate in 2010 and 2013
 - Team leader of the following strategic corporate projects (presented to the Company Board):
 - Conversion of the existing Fiumicino airport certificate in compliance with the Regulation (EU) 139/2014
 - Implementation of the "Fiumicino airport aviation risk project" for the mitigation of key risk areas of Airside, Terminal and Handling (on-going)
 - "Terminal safety analysis" for Fiumicino airport, developed with Roland Berger and Airport Research Center GmbH, as part of the "Fiumicino airport aviation risk project"
 - Project of reconfiguration the access and control processes of vehicle movement inside Fiumicino airport
 - Project of reconfiguration of goods deployment process inside the terminals of Fiumicino airport
 - Complex events managed:
 - A-320 Alitalia accident (landing without the right main landing gear) at Fiumicino airport on 29th Sep 2013
 - A-320 Wizzair accident (landing without the left main landing gear) at Fiumicino airport on 8th June 2013
 - ATR-72 Carpatair accident (off the runway on landing) at Fiumicino airport on 2nd February 2013
 - Aviapartner loader accident (fatal injury during loading operations) at Fiumicino airport on 11th Nov. 2012

- **⇒** Airport Committees chaired:
 - Fiumicino Airport Safety Committee
 - Ciampino Airport Safety Committee
 - Fiumicino Airport Local Runway Safety Team
 - Ciampino Airport Local Runway Safety Team
- Company Committees managed:
 - Company Safety Board, Committee consisting of the Accountable Manager, Safety Manager and Post Holders to ensure safety policy implementation
- Company delegate of the following associations:
 - Italian Airports Association "Safety" working group
 - Italian Flight Safety Committee (IFSC)

FROM SEPTEMBER 2004 TO AUGUST 2010 - AEROPORTO DI GENOVA S.P.A.

- Airport Safety Manager (10/2009 08/2010); Airport Safety Manager Deputy (10/2008 09/2009)
- Infrastructures and systems design Post Holder Deputy (09/2004 09/2009)
 - Main activities and responsibilities:
 - Implementation, management and development of the Safety Management System (SMS) of the airport
 - Coordination of the activities related to the CAA airports certification
 - Management of company Safety Board and airport Safety Committee
 - Carrying out projects of development and restoration of airside infrastructure including pavements and markings of runway, taxiways and aircraft apron
 - Compliance of the airside infrastructure initiatives with the national and international safety standards (CAA and ICAO) and management of related risk assessment
 - Management of technical data related to the physical characteristics of the airport
 - Training of airport staff to achieve the airside driving certificate and on safety management system
 - CAA airport certifications achieved:
 - Genoa Airport certificate in 2004 and three-year certificate renewal in 2007
 - Safety management system validation in 2010

FROM SEPTEMBER 2005 TO MARCH 2010: UNIVERSITY OF GENOA, FACULTY OF ENGINEERING

- Contract lecturer (ay 2006-2007); Lecturer of seminars (ay 2007-2008; ay 2005-2006)
- Assistant supervisor (ay 2008-2009; ay 2006-2007)
 - □ Lecturer of the Integrative Course "Elements to design an airport runway" as part of the Course "Air transportation 1" (ay 2006-2007), fifth year, Course of Civil Engineering
 - ⇒ Lecturer of seminars: "Elements to design an airport runway" (ay 2007-2008) and "Airport infrastructures" (ay 2005-2006) as part of the Course "Air transportation 1", fifth year, Course of Civil Engineering
 - Assistant supervisor of the MSc thesis: "Methods and criteria for the evaluation of rigid pavements of Genoa Airport" (ay 2008-2009); "Development of a damage mapping system for the scheduled maintenance of airport pavements. Case study of Genoa airport" (ay 2008-2009); "The airport safety management system—Theoretical aspects and practical subjects" (ay 2006-2007); "Structural design and maintenance planning of airport pavements. Analysis of the movement area of Genoa airport" (ay 2006-2007)

EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

- Civil Engineering Degree (transport specialization). Graduated on 23th March 2004 at the University of Genoa, Faculty of Engineering. Vote: 110/110 (publication recommended).
- Registered with the Italian Engineer Association since 13th September 2004

TRAINING

Attended over 20 courses within the company including national/international contests on management and leadership, quality systems, safety management system, auditing, accident/incident investigation

LANGUAGES

- Italian: native
- English: good writing and verbal skills

VOLUNTARY WORK

Voluntary activity in a small village in Nicaragua with the University Cooperation Institute (ICU) in August 2001